Guide to the Lars Onsager Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- PROJECTS & INSTITUTIONS, 1946-1976; Series V; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Atomic Energy Commission
    - General correspondence, 1971-1972, 1973 January-Apr, 1973 June-Dec, 1974 January-Dec, 1975 January-Jul, 1975 August-1976 (Box 22, Folder 5-13, Reel 13)
    - Research proposal, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 14, Reel 13)
    - Records of travel, 1970-1974, undated (Box 22, Folder 15, Reel 13)
    - Records and correspondence about security procedures, 1972-1976 (Box 22, Folder 16, Reel 13)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1957-1973 (Box 22, Folder 17, Reel 13)
    - Notes, undated (Box 22, Folder 18, Reel 13)
  - Fulbright Scholarship
    - Application and award, [1950?]-1951 (Box 22, Folder 19, Reel 13)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 22, Folder 20, Reel 13)
    - Gauss Professorship: correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 22, Folder 21, Reel 13)
    - Lorentz Professorship: correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 22, Folder 22, Reel 13)
  - National Institutes of Health
    - Research proposals and related correspondence, 1965-1976 (Box 23, Folder 23-24, Reel 13)
  - National Science Foundation
    - Correspondence and proposal, 1955-1966 (Box 23, Folder 25, Reel 13)
    - Correspondence and proposals, 1971-1976 (Box 23, Folder 26, Reel 13)
  - Neurosciences Research Program
    - General correspondence, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 27, Reel 13)
    - Brochures, undated (Box 24, Folder 28, Reel 13)
    - Reprints, 1967-1973 (Box 24, Folder 29, Reel 13)
    - Documentation for the Schmitt Lectureship Committee, 1973-1975 (Box 24, Folder 30, Reel 13)
    - Documentation for the Intensive Study Program, 1969-1976 (Box 24, Folder 31, Reel 13)
    - Index to Bulletin, Vol. 1-11, [1973?] (Box 24, Folder 32, Reel 13)
    - Science Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 24, Folder 33, Reel 13)
    - Documentation for work sessions in which Onsager participated, 1965-1974 (Box 24, Folder 34, Reel 13)
      See also: box 28, folder 10
    - Documentation for work sessions in which Onsager did not participate, 1969-1975 (Box 24, Folder 35, Reel 13)
    - Documentation for stated meetings of associates, 1969-1976 (Box 24, Folder 36-38, Reel 13)
    - Proposal for a research program "to make the mathematical tools of nonequilibrium statistical mechanics applicable to a quantitative description of the brain", undated (Box 24, Folder 39, Reel 13)
  - Office of Naval Research
    - Conference and program notes, 1946-1947, 1949-1950 (Box 25, Folder 40-41, Reel 13)
    - Administrative correspondence, 1951-1957 (Box 25, Folder 42, Reel 13)
  - University of Miami Center for Theoretical Studies
    - General correspondence, 1967, 1972, 1973, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 43, Reel 13)
    - Documentation for meetings of the Scientific Council, 1967-1976 (Box 25, Folder 44, Reel 13)
    - Administrative correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 25, Folder 45, Reel 13)
    - Letters from secretaries, 1973-1975 (Box 25, Folder 46, Reel 13)
    - Bulletin, 1967-1973 (Box 25, Folder 47, Reel 13)
    - Brochures containing general information, undated (Box 25, Folder 48, Reel 13)
    - Brochures describing the conferences on fundamental interactions, 1968-1973 (Box 25, Folder 49, Reel 13)
    - Photosynthetic energy production proposal by Sidney Fox, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 50, Reel 13)
  - Yale University
    - Chemistry Department mailings, 1962, 1970-1976 (Box 25, Folder 51, Reel 13)
    - Grant and Contract Administration mailings, 1961-1971 (Box 25, Folder 52, Reel 13)
    - Miscellaneous mailings, 1969-1975 (Box 25, Folder 53, Reel 13)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 25, Folder 54, Reel 13)
    - Tribute from the Dean of the Graduate School, 1972 (Box 25, Folder 54, Reel 13)
- AWARDS & HONORS, 1952-1976; Series VI; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series begins with papers related to the Nobel Prize. Papers related to other awards follow, in the order those awards were received.
  - Nobel Prize
    - List of congratulatory letters, [1968?] (Box 26, Folder 1, Reel 14)
    - Congratulatory letters
      - A-B, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 2, Reel 14)
      - C-D, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 3, Reel 14)
      - E-F, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 4, Reel 14)
      - G-H, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 5, Reel 14)
      - I-L, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 6, Reel 14)
      - M-N, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 7, Reel 14)
      - O-R, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 8, Reel 14)
      - S, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 9, Reel 14)
      - T-Z, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 10, Reel 14)
      - Multiple or incompletely identified senders, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 11, Reel 14)
    - List of congratulatory telegrams, [1968?] (Box 26, Folder 12, Reel 14)
    - Congratulatory telegrams
      - A-G, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 13, Reel 14)
      - H-P, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 14, Reel 14)
      - R-Z, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 15, Reel 14)
    - Printed acknowledgement of congratulations, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 16, Reel 14)
    - Transcript of reception at Yale, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 17, Reel 14)
    - Statement of Onsager's achievement, undated (Box 26, Folder 18, Reel 14)
    - Correspondence about arrangements in Sweden, 1968-1969, 1972-1976 (Box 26, Folder 19, Reel 14)
    - Programs and itineraries, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 20, Reel 14)
    - Tribute at the banquet, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 21, Reel 14)
    - Lecture
      - Correspondence re: publication, 1968-1972 (Box 26, Folder 22, Reel 14)
      - Preprints, notes on proofreading, 1969 (Box 26, Folder 23, Reel 14)
    - Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences: requests for nominations, 1969-1976 (Box 26, Folder 24, Reel 14)
    - Meetings at Lindau
      - Correspondence, documentation, lecture on "Protonic Semiconductors", 1967-1970 (Box 26, Folder 25, Reel 14)
        See: box 28, folder 8
      - Correspondence, programs, 1973, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 26, Reel 14)
    - Gustavus Adolphus College: correspondence re: convocation of Nobel laureates, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 27, Reel 14)
  - Rumford Medal: correspondence, program, presentation statement, 1952-1953 (Box 27, Folder 28, Reel 14)
  - Kirkwood Medal: correspondence, press release, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 29, Reel 14)
  - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute: correspondence re: honorary degree, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 30, Reel 14)
  - Gibbs Medal
    - Correspondence, 1961-1976 (Box 27, Folder 31-32, Reel 14)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 33, Reel 14)
    - Draft, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 34, Reel 14)
  - Debye Award: correspondence, tribute, 1964-1965 (Box 27, Folder 35, Reel 14)
  - Belfer Award: correspondence, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 35, Reel 14)
  - University of Chicago: letters re: honorary degree, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 36, Reel 14)
  - National Medal of Science: correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 27, Folder 37, Reel 14)
  - University of Cambridge: correspondence and program re: honorary degree, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 38, Reel 14)
  - Oxford University: correspondence and program re: honorary degree, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 39, Reel 14)
    See: box 28, folder 9
  - Seventieth birthday
    - Congratulatory letters, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 40, Reel 14)
    - Programs, lists of participants, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 41, Reel 14)
    - Papers presented, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 42, Reel 14)
- BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1938, 1953-1978; Series VII; 0.25; (1 box)
  The papers in this series are arranged in this order: memoirs, interview, clippings, photographs, family history. Each type of material is in chronological order.
  - Memoir by Philip A. Lyons, 1978 (Box 28, Folder 1, Reel 15)
  - "Lars Onsager," Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society, 1978 (Box 28, Folder 2, Reel 15)
  - Transcript of interview with Melvin L. Alexenberg on aesthetic experience in science, 1969 (Box 28, Folder 3, Reel 15)
  - Clippings, 1938, 1953-1978 (Box 28, Folder 4, Reel 15)
  - Photographs
    - International Conference on Theoretical Physics: group portrait, 1953 (Box 28, Folder 5, Reel 15)
    - Gordon Research Conferences: group portraits, 1955-1956 (Box 28, Folder 6, Reel 15)
    - Neurosciences Research Program: group portrait, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 7, Reel 15)
    - Meeting of Nobel laureates at Lindau: group portrait, candid photographs of Onsager with Dorothy C. Hodgkin and others, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 8, Reel 15)
    - Oxford University: snapshot, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 9, Reel 15)
    - France: snapshot, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 9, Reel 15)
    - Neurosciences Research Program: group portrait, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 10, Reel 15)
    - Unidentified meetings, [1974?], [1976?] (Box 28, Folder 11, Reel 15)
    - Gordon Research Conference: group portrait, 1976 (Box 28, Folder 12, Reel 15)
  - Copy of 1911 article about Onsager's [grandfather?], undated (Box 28, Folder 13, Reel 15)
- WRITINGS OF OTHERS, 1931-(1961-1976); Series VIII; 5 linear feet (12 boxes)
  The arrangement is alphabetical.
  - Ab-Ad (Box 29, Folder 1, Reel 16)
  - Ag-Ah (Box 29, Folder 2, Reel 16)
  - Ai-Al (Box 29, Folder 3, Reel 16)
  - American Chemical Society (Box 29, Folder 4-5, Reel 16)
  - An-Argonne (Box 29, Folder 6, Reel 16)
  - Argonne-Arm (Box 29, Folder 7, Reel 16)
  - Arn-Au (Box 29, Folder 8, Reel 16)
  - Bac-Barb (Box 30, Folder 9, Reel 16)
  - Bard-Bart (Box 30, Folder 10, Reel 16)
  - Bas-Baxter, G. (Box 30, Folder 11, Reel 16)
  - Baxter, R.J. (Box 30, Folder 12, Reel 16)
  - Baxter, R.J.-Ben (Box 30, Folder 13, Reel 16)
  - Ber-Bj (Box 30, Folder 14, Reel 16)
  - Bl-Bo (Box 30, Folder 15, Reel 16)
  - Bra-Bri (Box 30, Folder 16, Reel 16)
  - Bron (Box 30, Folder 17, Reel 16)
  - Broo-Bu (Box 31, Folder 18, Reel 16)
  - Ca (Box 31, Folder 19, Reel 16)
  - Ch-Cr (Box 31, Folder 20, Reel 16)
  - Da-De (Box 31, Folder 21, Reel 16)
  - Dh-Dre (Box 31, Folder 22, Reel 16)
  - Dro (Box 31, Folder 23, Reel 16)
  - Du (Box 31, Folder 24, Reel 16)
  - Ea-Eig (Box 31, Folder 25, Reel 16)
  - Ein-Ey (Box 31, Folder 26, Reel 16)
  - Fa-Fe (Box 32, Folder 27, Reel 16)
  - Fi (Box 32, Folder 28, Reel 16)
  - Fl-Fox, S. (Box 32, Folder 29, Reel 16)
  - Fox, S. (Box 32, Folder 30-31, Reel 16)
  - Fox, S.-Fu (Box 32, Folder 32, Reel 16)
  - Ga (Box 32, Folder 33, Reel 16)
  - Ge-Gi (Box 32, Folder 34, Reel 16)
  - Gl-Gu (Box 32, Folder 35, Reel 16)
  - Haa-Han (Box 33, Folder 36, Reel 16)
  - Har-Hepp, K. (Box 33, Folder 37, Reel 16)
  - Hepp, K. (Box 33, Folder 38, Reel 16)
  - Her (Box 33, Folder 39, Reel 16)
  - Hes-Hill (Box 33, Folder 40, Reel 16)
  - Hille, B. (Box 33, Folder 41, Reel 16)
  - Hille, B.-Hirsch (Box 33, Folder 42, Reel 16)
  - Hirschf-Hs (Box 33, Folder 43, Reel 16)
  - Hu (Box 33, Folder 44, Reel 16)
  - Hw (Box 34, Folder 45, Reel 16)
  - Hy (Box 34, Folder 46, Reel 16)
  - I (Box 34, Folder 47, Reel 16)
  - Ja-Jon (Box 34, Folder 48, Reel 16)
  - Jos-Ju (Box 34, Folder 49, Reel 16)
  - Kac (Box 34, Folder 50, Reel 16)
  - Kad (Box 34, Folder 51, Reel 16)
  - Kag-Kame (Box 34, Folder 52, Reel 16)
  - Kami-Kat (Box 34, Folder 53, Reel 16)
  - Ke-Ko (Box 34, Folder 54, Reel 16)
  - Kra-Krier, T. (Box 35, Folder 55, Reel 16)
  - Krier, T. (Box 35, Folder 56, Reel 16)
  - Krier, T.-Kru (Box 35, Folder 57, Reel 16)
  - Ku (Box 35, Folder 58, Reel 16)
  - La (Box 35, Folder 59, Reel 16)
  - Le (Box 35, Folder 60, Reel 16)
  - Lie-Lind (Box 35, Folder 61, Reel 16)
  - Ling-Liu (Box 35, Folder 62, Reel 16)
  - Lo-Ly (Box 35, Folder 63, Reel 16)
  - Mc (Box 36, Folder 64, Reel 16)
  - Mae-Man (Box 36, Folder 65, Reel 16)
  - Mar-Maz (Box 36, Folder 66, Reel 16)
  - Me-Mu (Box 36, Folder 67, Reel 16)
  - Nag (Box 36, Folder 68, Reel 16)
  - Nak-No (Box 36, Folder 69, Reel 16)
  - O (Box 36, Folder 70, Reel 16)
  - Pa (Box 36, Folder 71, Reel 16)
  - Pe-Ph (Box 36, Folder 72, Reel 16)
  - Pippard, A.B. (Box 37, Folder 73, Reel 16)
  - Pippard, A.B.-Pr (Box 37, Folder 74, Reel 16)
  - Rah-Rasetti, J. (Box 37, Folder 75, Reel 16)
  - Rasetti, M.-Re (Box 37, Folder 76, Reel 16)
  - Ri (Box 37, Folder 77, Reel 16)
  - Rob-Ros (Box 37, Folder 78, Reel 16)
  - Rot-Rue (Box 37, Folder 79, Reel 16)
  - Rum-Ry (Box 37, Folder 80, Reel 16)
  - Sa (Box 37, Folder 81, Reel 16)
  - Sc-Se (Box 38, Folder 82, Reel 16)
  - She-Shi (Box 38, Folder 83, Reel 16)
  - Sho (Box 38, Folder 84, Reel 16)
  - Si-Step (Box 38, Folder 85, Reel 16)
  - Stew-Stillinger, F. (Box 38, Folder 86, Reel 16)
  - Stillinger, F.-Stu (Box 38, Folder 87, Reel 16)
  - Su (Box 38, Folder 88, Reel 16)
  - Ta-Th (Box 38, Folder 89, Reel 16)
  - Ti-Tr (Box 38, Folder 90, Reel 16)
  - Uh-University of Virginia (Box 38, Folder 91, Reel 16)
  - University of Virginia (Box 39, Folder 92, Reel 16)
  - Up-Va (Box 39, Folder 93, Reel 16)
  - Ve-Vi (Box 39, Folder 94, Reel 16)
  - Vo-Vr (Box 39, Folder 95, Reel 16)
  - Wad (Box 39, Folder 96, Reel 16)
  - Wae-Web (Box 39, Folder 97, Reel 16)
  - Weg-Weik (Box 39, Folder 98, Reel 16)
  - Weinhold (Box 39, Folder 99, Reel 16)
  - Weit-Wh (Box 39, Folder 100, Reel 16)
  - Wic-Wilson, J. (Box 40, Folder 101, Reel 16)
  - Wilson, K. (Box 40, Folder 102, Reel 16)
  - Witt (Box 40, Folder 103, Reel 16)
  - Wo-Wu, S. (Box 40, Folder 104, Reel 16)
  - Wu, T.-Wy (Box 40, Folder 105, Reel 16)
  - Y (Box 40, Folder 106, Reel 16)
  - Z (Box 40, Folder 107, Reel 16)
  - Unidentified (Box 40, Folder 108, Reel 16)
- RESTRICTED MATERIAL
  - These boxes contain grades, letters of recommendation, minutes, grant proposals, and financial material found in the Lars Onsager Papers. This material was segragated prior to filming and is closed subject to review by the Associate Librarian. A list of the folders in these boxes is included in the "Register File". Consult the reference staff.
- Folio
  Oversize material: Series II, folders 57, 72, 140, and 189-227; Series III, folder 113